Guide to the Volunteers for Youth, Duke University Chapter Records, 1979-1984
Duke University. University Archives
Volunteers for Youth, Duke University Chapter records 1979-1984
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Volunteers for Youth.
0.5 linear feet Extent: 500 Items
The Duke University chapter of Volunteers for Youth was established around 1979 and was sponsored by the National Collegiate Athletic Association until the mid-1980s. Contains the records of the Duke University chapter of Volunteer for Youth, a service organization which paired student athletes with at-risk youth. Types of materials include agendas, meeting notes, lists of participants, training materials, handbooks, and newsletters. Major subjects include Duke University students, student athletes, community service, National Collegiate Athletic Association, and Volunteers for Youth. Materials range in date from 1979-1984.
RL.01931
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Volunteers for Youth, Duke University Chapter Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1987.
Historical Note
Volunteers for Youth, a national organization among colleges and universities, was started in 1969 at Stanford University. The Stanford Youth Program matched student athletes with junior high school-aged youth in the area. Youth received companionship and guidance from student athletes; students reported reaping personal rewards as well. In 1975, due to the overall success, former Stanford participants expanded the program to colleges and universities across the United States. Chapters were independently governed, and by 1977, some had failed because there was no national leadership. The National Collegiate Athletic Association agreed to sponsor Volunteers for Youth and funded four directors and staff members to serve chapters. The NCAA continued sponsorship through the mid-1980s. Individual colleges and universities sponsored programs from then on.
The Duke University program was established around 1979. Student athletes were paired with local middle school students, serving as role models for local children by taking them on outings and helping them in school. Some of the activities coordinated by the Duke University Volunteers for Youth were basketball clinics, picnics, film festivals, football games, and concerts. Volunteers for Youth was governed by 8-10 student directors, several advisors from Duke University and the city of Durham, and middle school counselors. When the NCAA discontinued sponsorship in the mid-1980s, the Duke University chapter offered volunteer opportunities to non-athletes.
As of 2003, Volunteers for Youth is affiliated with the Duke University Community Service Center, and provides volunteer opportunities for employees and students.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the Duke University chapter of Volunteers for Youth, a social service organization for students at Duke University. Materials range in date from 1979-1984.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
College athletes -- North Carolina; Duke University. Students; Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc; Duke University. Volunteers for Youth; National Collegiate Athletic Association; Social work with youth -- United States; Student volunteers in social service -- NorthCarolina.; Student service -- North Carolina
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Agendas and meeting notes, 1981-1983 (Folder 1)
  - Student director applications, circa 1984 (Folder 2)
  - Welcome packet for new Duke University volunteers, undated (Folder 3)
  - Program participant lists, circa 1979-1984 (Folder 4)
  - General chapter guidance, undated (Folder 5)
  - Summer seminars, 1982-1983 (Folder 6)
  - Volunteer handbook, 1984 (Folder 7)
  - Student director handbook, 1983 (Folder 8)
  - Duke University chapter newsletters, circa 1979-1984 (Folder 9)
  - National Volunteers for Youth newsletters, 1982-1984 (Folder 10)